<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Great case of the justices stated and determined touching their duty of putting the laws in execution, whether dissenters were indulg'd or not, or, A discourse concerning the oath of the justice of peace, explaining the extent of its obligation : being a case universally seasonable, in regard to righteousness, peace, and the prosperity of this nation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43213</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27024086</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27024086</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109917</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109917)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1718:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Great case of the justices stated and determined touching their duty of putting the laws in execution, whether dissenters were indulg'd or not, or, A discourse concerning the oath of the justice of peace, explaining the extent of its obligation : being a case universally seasonable, in regard to righteousness, peace, and the prosperity of this nation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.D. and are to be sold by Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 72.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with print show-through and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Oaths.</term>
               <term>Justices of the peace --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109917:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GREAT CASE OF THE JUSTICES <hi>Stated</hi> and <hi>Determined,</hi> TOUCHING Their Duty of putting the Laws in Execution, whether <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were Indulg'd, or Not. OR, A DISCOURSE con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the OATH of the <hi>Iuſtice of Peace,</hi> explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Extent of its Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Being a Caſe univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally ſeaſonable, in regard to Righteouſneſs, Peace, and the Proſperity of this Nation. <hi>Publiſhed with Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W.D.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:109917:2"/>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligation upon them, to the <hi>Execution</hi> of the <hi>Statutes</hi> of the <hi>Realm,</hi> having once <hi>Sworn</hi> thereunto, notwithſtanding the <hi>King's Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for <hi>Indulgence,</hi> (being ſhort of a <hi>Law</hi>); ſo that upon Suppoſition an <hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> was Legally
<pb facs="tcp:109917:2"/> brought, they could not forbear <hi>doing</hi> as they <hi>did formerly,</hi> without having an <hi>Ill Conſcience:</hi> And if there were no <hi>Volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> in <hi>Humane Affairs,</hi> to Diſturb the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in the Poſſeſsion of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Freedom,</hi> but that they might think
<pb facs="tcp:109917:3"/> themſelves ſo Safe and Inviolable, as to be out of Fear, That what <hi>Hath</hi> been, <hi>May</hi> be again: Yet were it a thing inſufferable, for a <hi>Diſſertation</hi> upon this Subject, which is ſo <hi>Elaborate,</hi> (being Written with ſuch <hi>Care,</hi> in weighing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing it ſets down,
<pb facs="tcp:109917:3"/> with ſo much feeling <hi>Tenderneſs,</hi> and pondered <hi>Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> with ſuch an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumen,</hi> yet <hi>Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Stile;</hi> and which hath been ſo well Adviſed, and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by the moſt Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of any I know), to be Caſt away, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as <hi>Water ſpilt
<pb facs="tcp:109917:4"/> on the Ground, which cannot be gathered up.</hi> But if, on the contrary, there be many <hi>Juſtices</hi> of that Perſwaſion, and amongſt a new ſet of <hi>Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices,</hi> there are ſome likely to be more Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in a <hi>point</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> than
<pb facs="tcp:109917:4"/> They; Then muſt this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <hi>Neceſſary</hi> at preſent, in regard to <hi>Such:</hi> And if the <hi>Fire</hi> that is pent up, does but Burn more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently, ſo that when the Indignation breaks out, it is likely to rage more furiouſly for the Reſtraint: And if the
<pb facs="tcp:109917:5"/> Lives of <hi>Princes</hi> (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when they are <hi>Benign</hi> and <hi>Good</hi>) are not certain to be longer, than other Mortals; Beſides, a multitude of other Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of <hi>Life,</hi> that go to the turning about that <hi>Wheel,</hi> which makes thoſe Perſons and Things, that are
<pb facs="tcp:109917:5"/> at the <hi>Top</hi> now, to be like to be at the <hi>Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom</hi> again, at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Seaſon; Then doth it ſeem <hi>Convenient</hi> alſo for <hi>Others,</hi> that we imitate the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident <hi>Houſholder,</hi> who ſets down a Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Receipt</hi> in his Book, for an Occaſion hereafter; though, at
<pb facs="tcp:109917:6"/> preſent, never a one of his <hi>Family</hi> hath need of it.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Caſe</hi> (Reader) is a <hi>Caſe</hi> of very great Moment, and Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and the <hi>Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> Singular, (for ſo would it have) been judged undoubtedly, if it bad come out at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Time): But the
<pb facs="tcp:109917:6"/> 
               <hi>Author</hi> has ſo man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged it, laying his <hi>Foundation</hi> ſo ſure, as he goes; and then raiſing his <hi>Structure</hi> ſo evenly upon it, that what is <hi>Difficult,</hi> he hath made appear <hi>Eaſie;</hi> and that which is <hi>Peculiar,</hi> he hath made appear as <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> ſo that every
<pb facs="tcp:109917:7"/> Body will be ready to ſay, He would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the <hi>Point</hi> juſt ſo himſelf; when there is a great deal more <hi>Study, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> goes into the Matter, than comes to Anothers ſhare to be Maſter of.</p>
            <p>I will note a few things. There is one
<pb facs="tcp:109917:7"/> ſhort <hi>Paragraph</hi> in the <hi>Book,</hi> (let the <hi>Reader</hi> find it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) which ſtates that Tickliſh Point of the <hi>King's Power</hi> about the <hi>Laws.</hi> He has written ſo Caſtigately on it, diſtinguiſhing the <hi>Negative</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Power,</hi> and offering his <hi>Notion</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:109917:8"/> in regard to the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good,</hi> (the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Law</hi>), that, I think, ſo compendious and clear a Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is not any where elſe to be found. I will by way of Confirmation thereof, add this Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Not long before the Death of the <hi>Late King,</hi> the <hi>Juſtices</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:109917:8"/> were ſending Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter</hi> to Priſon; but He, out of his kind Nature, (being told, That it would kill the good Man) ſent word im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately he ſhould be forborn. Should the <hi>King</hi> have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled the <hi>Law</hi> to his Hurt, it had been Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny;
<pb facs="tcp:109917:9"/> but when it was done only for his Good, with<hi rend="sup">out</hi> hurt to any, who is there will not juſtify the <hi>King</hi>'s aſſuming Power over <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Juſtices</hi> both, in that matter? To <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp <hi>Authority</hi> over the <hi>Law,</hi> only for the ſake of a Man's ſelf, as to take our <hi>Mony</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:109917:9"/> a <hi>Parliament,</hi> were the greateſt <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trociny,</hi> and which our <hi>King</hi> does abhor (who hath declared for his Subjects <hi>Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> as well as <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>): But for a <hi>King</hi> to declare his Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that He will have all his <hi>Subjects</hi> be <hi>Happy,</hi> and Enjoy
<pb facs="tcp:109917:10"/> their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> ſo long as the <hi>Publick</hi> receives no Detriment by it; and to that end, will <hi>forbear</hi> to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute</hi> ſuch and ſuch a Particular <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Laws,</hi> which appears to him <hi>prejudicial</hi> thereunto; I muſt ſay, after this Grave <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> That this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:109917:10"/> a thing altogether for the <hi>Welfare</hi> of his <hi>People,</hi> and not for his <hi>Perſonal Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,</hi> He muſt be ſaid to <hi>Govern</hi> ſtill <hi>Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law,</hi> ſeeing He does Act by the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Law,</hi> to which all Others are Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate, according to the Profound Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb facs="tcp:109917:11"/> of that <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another thing I will note, in regard to the <hi>Candor</hi> of this <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> who no doubt, does Write in Favour of the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> &amp; could not be pleaſed with any <hi>Cauſe</hi> or <hi>Party,</hi> who were for <hi>Perſecution;</hi> Yet
<pb facs="tcp:109917:11"/> does he, very purpoſely, Vindicate the Church of <hi>England,</hi> her <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy,</hi> and the <hi>Law,</hi> from the abuſe of ſuch <hi>Juſtices</hi> and curſed <hi>Informers,</hi> who (as they dealt with many People) did make them worſe than <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiſm;</hi> while they preſſed Them only to
<pb facs="tcp:109917:12"/> militate againſt the Sober Exerciſe of the the unqueſtionable du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> This <hi>Author</hi> will not have That which is barely the Fault of the <hi>One,</hi> to be Imputed to the <hi>Other.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Reader,</salute> I have no room to proceed to any further Note; but commit this Piece to Thy Hands, as a <hi>Jewel</hi> in my Opinion.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109917:12"/>
            <head>THE Juſtices CASE.</head>
            <p>THERE was a Book (I cannot tell juſt how many Years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, but it was at a time, I remember, when the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> were not troubled) which, together with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Books, was put out <hi>de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtria,</hi> toward the raiſing a Storm upon ſuch People: the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109917:13"/> Contents whereof came to this, That the <hi>Oaths</hi> of the late Times, the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Oath,</hi> the <hi>Engagement,</hi> were unlawful, and not to be kept; but the <hi>Oath</hi> which the <hi>Juſtices of Peace</hi> take, is unqueſtionable, and muſt oblige: And if they do not therefore Execute the Law to their utmoſt upon the <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> they are Perjur'd Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and muſt every Man of them, for ought I could ſee by that Book, be inevitably Damn'd.</p>
            <p>I am very apprehenſive, That His Majeſties <hi>Juſtices of Peace,</hi> throughout the Realm, are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle beholding to any Men for ſuch Diſcourſes. If they were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109917:13"/> to be ſuppoſed of that profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Conſcience, that they thought they might Swear any thing, and not be obliged to Perform what they Swear, then might ſuch a Book be Service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able (though not ſo much, I hope, as barely Reading over the <hi>Third Commandment</hi>): But if there be any thing of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Diſcernment required in an undertaking of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to yield the <hi>Reader</hi> the expected Fruit of eſtabliſhing his Conſcience, if he be a <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Peace,</hi> (whether <hi>Lord, Knight, Mayor, Alderman,</hi> or <hi>Gentleman</hi>) I muſt not wiſh any Body to ſeek it from that Book: Of which, as the <hi>Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109917:14"/> then did not name the <hi>Author,</hi> I will not now rake up the <hi>Title.</hi> Only the Diſtreſs of many Serious, Conſcientious, Pious <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> that are (or at leaſt have bin, or may be) called to this <hi>Office,</hi> in regard to the <hi>Taking</hi> and <hi>Keeping</hi> that <hi>Oath,</hi> which is then put upon them (in which Caſe, the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Conſtable</hi> alſo may be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in regard to <hi>His</hi>) does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a more Candid determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>In all <hi>Oaths</hi> that are <hi>Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory</hi> (we are to know) there are ſome <hi>Conditions</hi> to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, or underſtood, as the Ground of the Lawfulneſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109917:14"/> of ſuch <hi>Oaths,</hi> which elſe could be nothing but Snares to any good Men that took them. I do not think it <hi>eaſie</hi> preſently, nor <hi>needful,</hi> to reckon up all ſuch <hi>Conditions:</hi> But as for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the Laws of the Land, unto which the <hi>Juſtices</hi> Swear, there is this One moſt certain, <hi>viz.</hi> That theſe Laws ſtill be Executed <hi>in Subordination to the Supream Authority.</hi> There are ſeveral things might be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced, which a <hi>Juſtice</hi> is to do according to <hi>Law;</hi> when, upon Command <hi>from Above,</hi> he is to <hi>Surceaſe:</hi> His Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is Subordinate to the <hi>King;</hi> and the Laws to Almighty <hi>God. God</hi> now is the <hi>Supream Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109917:15"/> in the World; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, there is no Man takes ſuch an <hi>Oath</hi> to ſee the <hi>Laws Executed,</hi> but it muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood with Subordination to the Authority of <hi>Heaven,</hi> as that of the <hi>King.</hi> If therefore there be any thing in the Laws of the Land, that will not ſtand with our Duty to <hi>God,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> or his Revealed <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Juſtice</hi> is to be ſuppoſed that he Sware not to Execute <hi>That;</hi> but this <hi>Salvo</hi> is to be underſtood in his <hi>Oath, Saving the Rights of</hi> God <hi>Almighty, no leſs than thoſe of the Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ground of this does lye
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109917:15"/> a little more deep, than every one at firſt ſight does ſee: which is, That every thing that is ſuch, is not indeed <hi>Law.</hi> That which the <hi>Juſtice</hi> Swears to <hi>Execute,</hi> is the <hi>Law:</hi> But if this or that particular thing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by <hi>Man,</hi> be diſagreeable to the dictates of <hi>Nature,</hi> or the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which both are <hi>God's Will,</hi> ſuch a thing cannot be made <hi>Law,</hi> is no <hi>Law;</hi> and he is to look to himſelf, as not Sworn to perform it.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe the <hi>Juſtice</hi> will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily give his Ear to this, and it is thus confirmed. <hi>Power</hi> is a Right to Command. This Right is the Grant of the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109917:16"/> Authority. God</hi> is <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream</hi> of All. He does not grant that a Man, or any Men ſhould <hi>Command</hi> what he <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids.</hi> Whatſoever then is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable to his Will, cannot be <hi>Commanded,</hi> that is, cannot be <hi>Law;</hi> and the <hi>Juſtice</hi> Swears only to Execute <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I remember, a great while agoe, I applied my ſelf to a <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to deliver a <hi>Quaker</hi> out of Goal; I found him willing heartily, but he believed he might not, for fear of his <hi>Oath.</hi> I went away, not daring, if he thought ſo, to preſs him any more to it, but I thought upon it. I conſidered it was a hard
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109917:16"/> thing that Men by the <hi>Law</hi> ſhould be Impriſoned, and kept Year after Year, only for their <hi>Perſwaſion.</hi> I conſidered again, that <hi>Goodneſs</hi> which makes <hi>Men</hi> like <hi>God,</hi> the Rule of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs [<hi>Quod tibi non vis fieri, alteri, ne fieris</hi>], the Law of <hi>Love,</hi> and the Duties eſpecially of <hi>Mercy, Kindneſs, Gentleneſs,</hi> (which <hi>Chriſt</hi> requires of his Followers) did prompt to acts that are <hi>Contrary.</hi> I reſolved then, if the <hi>Law</hi> required one thing, and <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> or the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> another, the Law of God muſt take place; and no <hi>Oath</hi> conſequently could bind againſt <hi>God's Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:109917:17"/>
            <p>is to be Exerciſed: And the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue perhaps will come to this, That according as he believes, the ſparing or not ſparing ſuch <hi>made Faults</hi> (that is, <hi>Faults</hi> of <hi>Man's</hi> making by <hi>Law,</hi> upon ſuch extrinſical accounts, and not <hi>God's</hi>) to be conducive to thoſe ends (if they be good) he is to be guided in his actings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> binds the People with a Curſe, <hi>That they ſhall not Eat till the Evening: Jonathan,</hi> knowing nothing of this, Eats; and upon Lot and Diſcovery is Commanded to be Slain. The People, for all this <hi>Oath,</hi> will not Execute that Law or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but ſave <hi>Jonathan.</hi> Now
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109917:17"/> look, what would juſtifie the <hi>People</hi> in refuſing Obedience to that <hi>Oath,</hi> will acquit the <hi>Juſtice;</hi> who upon the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count (for all his <hi>Oath</hi>) does not Execute ſome Law of the Realm. The People thought it a raſh Determination, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Sentence, and a Sinful Command againſt the <hi>Sixth Commandment,</hi> that the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſhould be Puniſhed. It had been <hi>Murder,</hi> if they had purſued the <hi>Oath.</hi> And upon that account, we are to judge <hi>Saul</hi> reproved of his unadviſed Curſe, and he bound to Repent, but no body to Execute what he had Sworn: And yet all of them, nevertheleſs, bearing ſtill
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109917:18"/> the ſame Faith and Allegiance to the <hi>Anointed of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you deſire more than this, I will diſtinguiſh in the next place between the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of it; the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Purpoſe</hi> of it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which it receives its Conſtruction. If a <hi>Juſtice of Peace</hi> does act according to the <hi>Intent</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> I do apprehend he does perform his <hi>Oath</hi> better than if he rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſtood upon the <hi>Letter.</hi> Nay, he may contract Guilt upon himſelf in the <hi>One,</hi> when he ſhall not in the <hi>Other.</hi> The <hi>Laws</hi> now againſt the <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> I apprehend to ſtand in general
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109917:18"/> upon this <hi>Reaſon,</hi> They would have them come to <hi>Church,</hi> and ſecure the Peace of the Nation. If a <hi>Juſtice</hi> then apprehend, that the uſing of Rigour will but drive more from the <hi>Church,</hi> and enkindle diſturbance; I ask, Whether he be moſt obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the obſervation of his <hi>Oath,</hi> to <hi>Forbearance</hi> or <hi>Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution?</hi> Severity, it is true, hath been found a little of late (as it ſo happened) to have done ſomething: But at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, with other Perſons, where the Conſcience is Steel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it hath done, and it can do juſt nothing, unleſs where it is <hi>Over-Cruel;</hi> and that makes <hi>Deſolation,</hi> and at long running,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109917:19"/> doth but widen the breach. <hi>Solitudinem faciunt, &amp; pacem vocant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Though the <hi>Law</hi> paſs in <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Executive part</hi> is committed to the <hi>King.</hi> I will ſuppoſe now a <hi>Prince</hi> to be of the Mind, that <hi>Tenderneſs</hi> is like to be more conducive to the Good theſe Laws deſign, than <hi>Violence,</hi> or to be in his Judgment againſt Perſecution: I ask then, Whether the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> who acts under the <hi>King,</hi> might not ſatisfie his Conſcience in this, That he ſhall, according as he Judges, by <hi>Indulgence</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than by <hi>Rigour,</hi> beſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the <hi>Will</hi> of the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109917:19"/> Governour?</hi> I remember well, in the time of the late King, That I my ſelf once heard Him, with my own Ears, declare at Council-Board, and that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly, (for he roſe up, ſaying ſo), <hi>That He was againſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting any for their Conſciences.</hi> This I take to have been his <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Judgment;</hi> and whatſoever his <hi>Adventitious Practice</hi> might be, upon the Scene-altering, there are none but muſt confeſs both alike favourable, at the time of his <hi>Declaration to his Loving Subjects;</hi> which is not ſo many Years paſt, as to be out of our Remembrance.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:109917:20"/>
            <p>rightly, according to a Mans Conſcience, not erring intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably, is) inſtead of <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Ill-doing:</hi> I do ask, How can the <hi>Juſtice</hi> be bound by his <hi>Office</hi> to do that which does prevent the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> it ſelf?</p>
            <p>But let us ſuppoſe a <hi>Juſtice of Peace,</hi> who is of the mind that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are ill Men, and their <hi>Conventicles</hi> not to be endured: I pray let me ſee this <hi>Juſtice</hi> as Zealous alſo againſt Prophaneneſs, Swearing, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, and Debauchery of all ſorts, which are Offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law, and alike Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by him: or elſe, if the Man be ſo <hi>Hot</hi> for Reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109917:20"/> 
               <hi>Meetings,</hi> but <hi>Cold</hi> for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing <hi>Vice,</hi> I can hardly think, that what he does is done meerly out of Conſcience of his <hi>Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a Law, That a <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt</hi> may not abide with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Five Miles of a <hi>Corporate</hi> Town: What now if his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs brings him thither, and he cannot poſſibly live elſe? Is this a piece of <hi>Evil-doing,</hi> unto which the Ruler ſhould be a <hi>Terror?</hi> Suppoſe an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former</hi> ſhould come to a <hi>Juſtice of Peace,</hi> and Swear againſt a <hi>Brewer</hi> for Brewing with <hi>Hops:</hi> There is a Law made againſt That, as I have taken it up,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109917:21"/> (though it may not be in the ordinary Book of <hi>Statutes,</hi> which pretends only to <hi>Collect</hi> thoſe which are <hi>fit for uſe</hi>), and the <hi>Juſtice</hi> Swears, <hi>He will do his Office after the Statutes of the Realm:</hi> I will ask now, Upon what account can any equal <hi>Juſtice</hi> diſmiſs ſuch a <hi>Brewer,</hi> and not Puniſh him upon that Complaint; but he may, upon the ſame, diſmiſs a <hi>Nonconformiſt,</hi> who is accuſed of being in a <hi>Corporation,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his <hi>Oath?</hi> If a thing be not <hi>Evil,</hi> it is againſt <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> to Puniſh it. No <hi>Law</hi> but muſt give place to <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> no <hi>Oath</hi> can bind againſt it.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:109917:21"/>
            <p>I would put it here to the queſtion, Whether the not coming within Five Miles of a <hi>Corporation,</hi> as the <hi>Brewing</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Ingredients of <hi>Beer,</hi> be matters of that Nature as ought to be brought within the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a <hi>Law,</hi> any more than that a Man ſhall not make Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt a Wall? <hi>Quod non habet rationem publici commodi, non poteſt proecipi lege humana.</hi> I would make it a <hi>Moot Caſe</hi> at the <hi>Inns of Court,</hi> as well as a <hi>Probleme</hi> in the <hi>Schools.</hi> What is unreaſonable, methinks, ſhould be againſt <hi>Nature,</hi> and cannot be commanded for a <hi>Law,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Laws</hi> are grounded upon <hi>Reaſon.</hi> I will not be ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109917:22"/> bold as to averr, That the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of ſuch an Act does Claſh with <hi>Magna Charta, Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus liber homo capiatur, impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur, aut diſſeiſietur de tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento, vel libertatibus utlege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, exulatur, aut aliquo modo deſtruatur, niſi per legem Terrae:</hi> But if it does but claſh with that which ought to be the end of every Commandment, (<hi>The end of the Commandment is Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>), it will be more certainly enough to take off the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> See Dr. <hi>Taylor. Duc. Dub. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>But I muſt advance a ſtep farther: I do not apprehend
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109917:22"/> only, That when the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a <hi>Law</hi> will not conſiſt with the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>God's Word,</hi> that is, with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and <hi>Moral Good,</hi> but when it will not ſtand with that <hi>Political Good</hi> which the <hi>Law</hi> intends, the Magiſtrate is not in that caſe to obſerve it. For, when the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices</hi> are bound to ſee the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the <hi>Laws,</hi> they are not to be look'd on as <hi>Blind, Brutiſh</hi> Executioners of them; but that they muſt judge of them on neceſſity, ſo far as concerns their <hi>own acting</hi> about them. The <hi>King</hi> muſt judge whether the matter be good for his <hi>paſſing</hi> the <hi>Law.</hi> The
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109917:23"/> 
               <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Juſtices</hi> muſt judge, whether it be ſtill good, as to the <hi>Execution.</hi> Nay, every ſingle Man muſt <hi>Judge</hi> of the Laws made, ſo far as concerns his <hi>own Obeying</hi> them; ſeeing, <hi>If he be bound to do nothing that is ill, he muſt likewiſe be bound before he does any thing, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf whether he does ill or no;</hi> as is very <hi>honeſtly</hi> ſaid, though in an <hi>adverſe</hi> Book, Entituled, <hi>Toleration Diſcuſs'd;</hi> which came out about the ſame time with the Book at firſt intimated, but not named.</p>
            <p>By the way, We muſt upon neceſſity obſerve here, the Caſe being brought on to this ſtate;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109917:23"/> That the <hi>King,</hi> as well as the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> is concern'd in it. There is therefore the <hi>Poſitive</hi> and <hi>Negative</hi> Power of the <hi>King,</hi> and there are matters <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi> It is true, That the Government of <hi>England,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Government Regulated by Laws,</hi> and that the <hi>King</hi> can <hi>Poſitively</hi> do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>according to Law:</hi> But there is this other thing to be known and conſidered alſo, That the great <hi>Law,</hi> the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream <hi>Law</hi> in all Polities, is the <hi>Common Good.</hi> And in the uſe of that Power which is <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> or in <hi>Suſpending his own Act</hi> (which the not permiting a Proceſs in his Name, or the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109917:24"/> granting a <hi>Nolle proſequi</hi> (I think) is no other) in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of his Government (at leaſt in matters <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> wherein he hath all that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given him by the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,</hi> as the <hi>Pope</hi> ever had) a Prince is never to be ſaid, <hi>Not to Govern according to Law,</hi> when he does only give Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence to <hi>That</hi> which is the <hi>Greateſt,</hi> the Weal of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity. <hi>Salus Populi Suprema Lex eſto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much being ſaid in referrence to the <hi>King,</hi> Let any one that pleaſe, reaſon what will follow, in regard to the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> who is but an Officer
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109917:24"/> (I ſuppoſe) under Him, to act in his ſtead, and in his Name. If the Magiſtrate then (to go on), whether <hi>Supream</hi> or <hi>Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> does judge that ſuch or ſuch a <hi>Law</hi> be good, and good to be executed, that is, That the Execution of it will tend to the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in it (as in all Laws it muſt be), and that it is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality</hi> (in which caſe the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Law does vacate this), then is he to look to himſelf, and what he hath Sworn; knowing that <hi>God</hi> will not <hi>hold him Guiltleſs,</hi> that <hi>beareth the Sword,</hi> and much leſs him that <hi>taketh his Name</hi> alſo <hi>in vain.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:109917:25"/> But if he judge ſincerely in his Conſcience, That the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will not be for the Good, but rather Hurt to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the People, (though otherwiſe the thing be not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful), I do apprehend the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution</hi> of his <hi>Office,</hi> in this caſe, does lye in the <hi>Non-Execution</hi> of that <hi>Law</hi> (if the Higher Powers be contented), and he ſhall do his Duty, by leaving ſuch work <hi>undone.</hi> I have heard that ſome <hi>Judges,</hi> in their Charge to the <hi>Jury,</hi> have given Directions to Proſecute the <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> upon <hi>One Statute</hi> of the Queen, and not upon ſome <hi>Other;</hi> which, in effect, is a ſuſpending <hi>that Law</hi> at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109917:25"/> and juſtifies this Plea.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Oath</hi> which the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> takes, for the Executing his Office, the words run thus; <hi>You ſhall do equal Right to Rich and Poor, after your Cunning, Wit, and Power.</hi> By which Word [<hi>Cunning</hi>] continued from Antient Uſe, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not ſo much according to the beſt of a Mans <hi>Skill</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> which is compriſed rather in the Word [<hi>Wit</hi>]; But according to the beſt of his <hi>Diſcretion, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Prudence;</hi> which includes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i.e. <hi>Candor, Moderation,</hi> in Caſes that require it: That is, <hi>You ſhall well and truly do
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:109917:26"/> trary to the Law of Nature and Reaſon, loſe their force, and are no Laws at all;</hi> Finch's <hi>Law,</hi> p. 75. <hi>The Law of Nature and Reaſon is unchangeable and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual, and no Statute can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt it;</hi> Doctor and Student, p. 4. <hi>Conſtat profecto ad ſalutem civium vitamque omnium beatam conditas eſſe leges</hi> (ſays <hi>Cicero</hi>): <hi>Ex quo intelligi par eſt eos qui pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſa populis juſſa deſcripſerint, quodvis potius tuliſſe quam leges;</hi> in his two excellent Books, <hi>De Legibus,</hi> which have, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, given the firſt Light to all things, almoſt, which our <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Lawyers</hi> have ſaid well on this Subject. I will
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109917:26"/> add St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and turn to no more: <hi>Mihi lex eſſe non videtur quae juſta non fuerit; De</hi> Lib. Arb. l. 1. c. 5.</p>
            <p>After theſe Teſtimonies, it is yet needful I explain the thing a little more, for which I bring them. When I ſay, therefore, That a Command or Law made againſt <hi>Charity, Righteouſneſs,</hi> the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> is <hi>No Law;</hi> I underſtand not, but that any <hi>Bill</hi> which paſſes the <hi>Houſes,</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> is a <hi>Law,</hi> or <hi>Statute</hi> of the <hi>Realm;</hi> that is, a <hi>Law</hi> in <hi>Foro Humano,</hi> in <hi>Mans Court,</hi> or at the <hi>Bar in Weſtminſter;</hi> and if any <hi>Juſtice</hi> will Execute it, the <hi>Outward</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:109917:27"/> Publicum: <hi>And conſequently, if a Law prove otherwiſe, or is againſt the Common Good; it muſt be ſuppoſd, alſo, That ſuch a Law is devoid of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, or is not according to their Will; and ſo does not bind the Conſcience, even upon a double ground; both becauſe it is deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the Authority it ſhould have from</hi> God, <hi>and its Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the</hi> Will of Man <hi>alſo, upon the account already given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any Man now riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, with a <hi>But who ſhall be Judge?</hi> he may return to his Seat, unleſs he chooſe to be a <hi>Bruit;</hi> ſeeing every man (according to the Religion of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109917:27"/> 
               <hi>Proteſtnnts</hi>) muſt be allowed a Judgment of <hi>Private Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to be his Guide, in all which himſelf acts: And if, when a thing is commanded him, he muſt judge, whether it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Word</hi> (which is ſo much harder), how much rather, whether it be aggree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>Right Reaſon</hi> (which is the Law of Nature) and the <hi>Common Good?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were two <hi>Laws</hi> made in the latter Long-Parliament, One about <hi>Burying in Woollen,</hi> and the Other about <hi>Waggons;</hi> Neither of which were at firſt regarded: But the <hi>Woollen</hi> Act being found good for the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:109917:28"/> was renewed, and is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; but the Other not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, is neglected; that is, as to the <hi>number</hi> of <hi>Horſes,</hi> very frequently; but as to the <hi>breadth</hi> of the <hi>Wheels,</hi> altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I ask now, Whether the <hi>Waggoner,</hi> that makes no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience how many <hi>Horſes</hi> he puts in his <hi>Waggon,</hi> no more than of the dimenſion of his <hi>Wheels,</hi> and breaks this <hi>Law,</hi> does ſin in it? If he does, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he does it every day, and continues without amendment, how can he be Saved? If it be no Sin, becauſe the <hi>Common Good</hi> ſuperſedes the <hi>Law;</hi> I ask, Who then is <hi>Judge,</hi> whether this <hi>Law</hi> be for the Publick
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109917:28"/> Good, or not? It is plain, the Man himſelf finds the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of it, and he <hi>judges</hi> what is good for his <hi>Waggon,</hi> and can do it better than they that <hi>Paſſed</hi> the <hi>Act;</hi> and ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders his matters accordingly. Suppoſe then, an <hi>Informer</hi> comes to the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and Swears againſt him; the <hi>Juſtice</hi> may Puniſh him if he will; but he, judging it no ways conducive to the <hi>Publick Advantage,</hi> as well as the <hi>Waggoner</hi> (at leaſt, not ſo much as can countervail the private damage of the Poor Man), lets him go. Here the <hi>Juſtice of Peace</hi> does <hi>judge</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> in regard to his <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> of it; and the <hi>Waggoner</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:109917:29"/> put Fear into the Heart of Man, to be the Inſtrument by which his <hi>Vicegerents</hi> Govern the World.</p>
            <p>And now, having ſtated the Caſe I took in hand, as near as I can to my Mind, I will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the moſt of ſuch <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,</hi> who are in <hi>Commiſſion</hi> for the <hi>Peace</hi> (if they may chooſe), would be willing to live quiet with their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; and if they may enjoy <hi>Their own Conſciences,</hi> be loath to vex others about <hi>Theirs;</hi> but yet, That there are ſome of <hi>another Make,</hi> who either out of <hi>Hatred</hi> to the <hi>Conventiclers,</hi> or <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Senſe</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:109917:29"/> of their <hi>Office,</hi> or <hi>Inſtigation</hi> of <hi>Others,</hi> or put upon it by ſome <hi>Informer,</hi> are ſtill for the <hi>Executing</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> againſt the <hi>Diſſenting Meeter:</hi> I muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, take upon me to argue a little with the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of this ſort, and ask him two Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; What a <hi>Conventicle</hi> is? and, In what <hi>Manner</hi> he will proceed?</p>
            <p>For the former, The <hi>Act</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Conventicles</hi> declares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all <hi>Aſſembling under Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour or Pretence of any Exerciſe of Religion, in other manner than according to the Liturgy and Practice of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: And the <hi>Oxford Act</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109917:30"/> ſuch Meetings as, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Colour of any Exerciſe of Religion, are contrary to the Laws and Statutes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> It is not all Meetings then of above Four, that are not of the ſame Family, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form a Religious Exerciſe, are <hi>Conventicles;</hi> but ſuch as can be proved to be <hi>in other manner than according to the Liturgy and Practice of the Church;</hi> or, are <hi>contrary to the Laws of the Kingdom.</hi> The Church and Law now of <hi>England,</hi> does own the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and Gods Word commandeth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Exerciſes at home and abroad, as well as <hi>Church-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Chriſt</hi> Prayed and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109917:30"/> on Mountains, in Houſes in Ships; and ſo did his Diſciples. <hi>Cornelius</hi> called together his <hi>Kinsfolks</hi> and <hi>Friends</hi> to hear <hi>Peter.</hi> The Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>To Exhort one another daily, and to conſider one another to provoke to good Works.</hi> The Thirteenth Canon requires <hi>all Perſons to Celebrate the Lords Day,</hi> not only by <hi>Publick,</hi> but <hi>Private</hi> Prayer, <hi>Confeſſing</hi> their <hi>Sins, Reconciling</hi> themſelves Charitably to their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> and uſing all Godly Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions, 1559. allows a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter <hi>at all times, when neceſſity requires, to comfort his Flock with the lively Word of God,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109917:31"/> which is the ſtay of Man's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> Moreover, The <hi>Church</hi> hath appointed the <hi>Pſalms</hi> in <hi>Metre,</hi> for Private Houſes, Forms of Prayer, bound up with the <hi>Bible,</hi> the <hi>Practice of Piety, Nowel's Catechiſm, Jewel's Works,</hi> to be kept in every Pariſh, where more than Four may Read them. If more than <hi>Four</hi> or <hi>Forty</hi> meet to Feaſt together, the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Liturgy</hi> forbids them not to give Thanks for their Meat, no, nor to Pray, or read the <hi>Scripture,</hi> or a Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Book,</hi> or Sing a <hi>Pſalm,</hi> if they will, at the end of their Supper. If any one then ſhall go to turn the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> by threatning
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:109917:31"/> Godly Perſons for doing theſe things, and would ſeduce the <hi>Juſtice</hi> to Proſecute them for it, with Mulcts and Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let the Accuſation be heard. Is it for the <hi>meer num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of ſuch that meet, that they muſt be made Criminal, or for the <hi>Faultineſs of the Thing</hi> that they meet about? It cannot be for the <hi>meer number,</hi> becauſe there are more allowed to meet at a <hi>Play-Houſe,</hi> a <hi>Seſſions-Houſe,</hi> an <hi>Exchange,</hi> at an <hi>Horſe-Race,</hi> a <hi>Cock-Match,</hi> a <hi>Bull-Baiting,</hi> a a <hi>Bear-Baiting,</hi> an <hi>Hunting,</hi> an <hi>Execution,</hi> in the <hi>Street,</hi> in a <hi>Ship.</hi> It muſt be the <hi>unlawful Exerciſe,</hi> then, muſt make it a Crime, or nothing; for to <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109917:32"/> Exerciſes</hi> no Limits are ſet. And what, I pray, then is that? If it be only reading <hi>God</hi>'s Word to more than Four, beſides the Family; that is not unlawful; nor a Licenſed Book, no, nor Repeating a <hi>Sermon;</hi> for, where does the <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Liturgy</hi> forbid either of them? If Men <hi>Meet to call themſelves adiſtinct Church, and to form Rules of Diſcipline, and Impeach the Government or Liturgy;</hi> This indeed, the Canon forbids, and makes it the Character of a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> and ſo expounds the <hi>Name.</hi> Tutors may Catechize more at once than Four; and more than Four may joyn in Prayer: If a God-Father have Four and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:109917:32"/> Four God-Children, may he not, after they are Sixteen Years of Age, Exhort them together to perform their Vow, which he made in their Name at <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> May not more than Four to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether give <hi>God</hi> Thanks at a Table? More than Four Travel together, or Viſit; and are they forbidden Religious Conference, to Edifie one another? Should the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> forbid this, what were the <hi>Church</hi> but an <hi>Anti-Church,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> the <hi>Devil's Militia,</hi> to Fight againſt Piety, and Mens Salvation?</p>
            <p>Well then, The <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> not forbidding, but allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things, I come, in the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109917:33"/> next place, to inquire how the <hi>Juſtice</hi> will proceed; for I will conceive him to be a Man of Temper, who acts with Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Righteouſneſs, with Care and Conſcience in what he does.</p>
            <p>If any Witneſs will Swear only in general, That above <hi>Four met for Religious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, in other manner than the Church and Law alloweth;</hi> either they muſt Swear alſo what that <hi>unlawful Exerciſe</hi> was, or they do not. <hi>If not,</hi> the Liberties of <hi>Engliſh-Men</hi> are brought to a ſine paſs, when two Perſons, that liſt, may take them away, and undo Folks at their Will.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109917:33"/> Is it thus, beſides, in all the Courts of <hi>Juſtice?</hi> Do they Hang Men as <hi>Felons,</hi> when any will but Swear that they are <hi>Felons,</hi> and never tell what they Stole, nor from whom? Will the Lords Condemn a Peer for Treaſon, if two will Swear that he ſpake Treaſon, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tell what Words he ſpake? Will the <hi>Church</hi> excommunicate a Man, if two will Swear that he is a Murderer, but cannot tell of any body he Murdered? <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> abhor ſuch doings, as we abhor <hi>Toads</hi> and <hi>Snakes. If they Swear what the unlawful Exerciſe was,</hi> it is ſuppoſed they are but <hi>Witneſſes</hi> and <hi>Accuſers,</hi> and not the <hi>Judges.</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:109917:34"/> If every Woman or Beggar, that can but Swear, does be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Judge,</hi> whether the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Acts of Lords, Knights, Miniſter and People, be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> or not, when they know not what the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> is; it were far better be among <hi>Serpents</hi> and <hi>Tygers,</hi> than for People to have their Eſtates and Lives at the Will of ſuch Perſons: for, who dare then diſpleaſe any Beggar, Rogue, or Servant? It is not the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> therefore, but the <hi>Juſtice</hi> is <hi>Judge;</hi> and he muſt Examine the Witneſs, (ſeeing elſe he muſt become but a <hi>Regiſter</hi> or <hi>Executioner</hi>), and that muſt be of two things;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109917:34"/> What the <hi>unlawful Exerciſe</hi> was? (as is already Suggeſted) and how the Witneſs knoweth it?</p>
            <p>He muſt examine firſt, <hi>What the unlawful Exerciſe was?</hi> If they ſay now, There was a Meeting, and plead Notoriety of Fact: So is there at a <hi>Play,</hi> at a <hi>Market,</hi> in a <hi>Ship,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch greater Meetings, as are before-named. If they ſay, There was Notoriety of a <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi> Meeting: So is there in all <hi>Church</hi>-Meetings, in Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings only for Houſe-Prayer, Holy Conference, Grace at Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the like, not forbidden; which are alſo before touched. At <hi>Doctors-Commons</hi> they do
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109917:35"/> meet about Admoniſhing, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating, Abſolving, and theſe are certainly <hi>Religious</hi> Exerciſes, of Grand Importance; and yet performed without reading <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi> Either the Crime that Men are Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for, is <hi>Omiſſion</hi> of ſomething <hi>required;</hi> or <hi>Commiſſion</hi> of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>forbidden.</hi> The <hi>Omiſſion</hi> of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> cannot here be Criminal, becauſe the reading <hi>That,</hi> is required in <hi>Church</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; but it is not impoſed on <hi>Private</hi> Perſons, and Places, Families, Converſe, or Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Meetings: And there is no Crime of <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe neither the bare number of Men, nor any of theſe Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109917:35"/> before-named, (and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed only here uſed), are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. If they ſay, That the <hi>Law</hi> forbids not above Four to be at a Play, a Tavern, a Feaſt; but it forbids all above Four, of another Houſe, to be at any Religious Meeting, it is a Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for the <hi>Law</hi> never forbid more than Four to be at <hi>Any Religious</hi> Exerciſe, but <hi>Forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> Exerciſes, which differ from the <hi>Church Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Practice;</hi> which none of the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Exerciſes do.</p>
            <p>The other thing the Witneſs muſt be Examined upon, is, <hi>How they know the Accuſation to be true?</hi> And if it be <hi>Omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:109917:36"/> of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> that they Swear, they muſt Swear they were preſent from firſt to laſt, elſe they cannot Swear, that it was not Read; and Men muſt not be Judged and Ruined up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Preſumptions and Opinions of others, without Proof: If <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> is ſaid to be omitted, (even in <hi>Church</hi>) they muſt Swear <hi>which Part.</hi> But if they be Crimes of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> that are Sworn, the Words and Deeds muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, with all that is Integral to the Senſe, before any Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be given. It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Humanity, Law, or Reaſon, that any Man ſhould be refuſed to ſpeak for himſelf,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:109917:36"/> and ſee his Accuſers Face to Face, and know what they are, and have leave to put Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories to them. If you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, That Leave to know the Accuſers and Witneſs, will hazard and diſcourage them, and Leave to plead for ones Self, it may fruſtrate all, both Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Execution. I anſwer, If indeed you ſtick there, you are not the Man I took you for, that is, no fair Man; and if that be the Rule you would go by, I will tell you, there is a nearer way than yours yet: Never ſtand troubling us, or your ſelf with <hi>Laws, Courts, Judge,</hi> or <hi>Witneſſes;</hi> but take all Mens Goods and Money that you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:109917:37"/> have a mind to, or Impriſon or Hang up any Man that you will, without giving any Reaſon or account for it. It will be conſiderable Clemency to a Man to let him Dye as Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and eſcape the Infamy of Accuſation. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles had not ſo much <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are things that the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> who is of the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Perſwaſion, is to think up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and if he be a <hi>London Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> there is one thing more to be put to him. There are at leaſt a Hundred, or two Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thouſand Souls in the great Pariſhes, in and about
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109917:37"/> 
               <hi>London,</hi> more than can hear in the Churches: I ask him now, Would you have all, or half theſe Perſons to live as Atheiſts, and Worſhip <hi>God</hi> in no manner at all, in any Congregation, or would you not? If you would not, Why do you Proſecute them for going to Private Meetings, when they cannot come to the Publick, in their own <hi>Church,</hi> which will not hold them? If you would, I deſire, <hi>Sir,</hi> then very fairly to have done with you; for it were better to have to do with a <hi>Mahometan,</hi> than with a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of ſuch a Mind.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:109917:38"/>
            <p>After this, I muſt return to the ſtate of our Caſe, to touch it again in the main Point. If any Law of <hi>Man</hi> be inconſiſtent with <hi>God's Will,</hi> either mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly by the Light of <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſuch a Law ſhould not have paſſed by the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver,</hi> and is not to be Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Inferior <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> or obſerved by the <hi>People:</hi> But if the Matter of a Law be ſuch, as is of an indifferent Nature, and, all Circumſtances conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it does appear doubtful and difficult to us, what we are to do: There is ſome Rule to be laid down, on neceſſity, to walk by, or we are at a loſs. Now, as <hi>God</hi> hath given us a <hi>Rule</hi> in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109917:38"/> Matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> which is the <hi>Scripture,</hi> by which we are to judge and try what is to be Believed and Practiſed therein; and every Man's own Private Judgment or Conſcience muſt be the Diſcerner of it: And as in <hi>Moral</hi> things He hath given us the Dictates of <hi>Reaſon</hi> for our Rule: So in Matters that are <hi>Political,</hi> hath He given us our Rule or Teſt alſo which is the <hi>Publick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility,</hi> (for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, ſpeaking of the Higher Powers, that give <hi>Laws,</hi> or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Ruler, does tell us, That he is <hi>the Miniſter of</hi> God <hi>for our Good,</hi> as I have noted); and Man being a Creature endued with Diſcernment, by his Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109917:39"/> Faculties, he is to attend, and compare ſuch things with that Rule; And as they agree, or not agree thereunto, he is to <hi>Paſs</hi> to <hi>Execute,</hi> to <hi>Obey</hi> a Law, or <hi>Not</hi> to do it, accordingly. This is a Truth, I am perſwaded, or Light, that I have ſtruck out of the Colliſion of many Thoughts; and do propoſe it therefore, as Taſted, Clear, Fixed, and Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, to Others. When a thing now (to proceed upon it) is really againſt the <hi>Common Good,</hi> or a Man ſo judges (his Judgment not being the <hi>Rule</hi> it ſelf, but the <hi>Diſcerner</hi> of it), ſuch a thing (at leaſt, to that Man) is never to be thought to have the <hi>Authority of God</hi> (as that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109917:39"/> 
               <hi>Religion</hi> hath none of it, which hath not Foundation in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>), nor indeed the <hi>Intent of Man</hi> (this <hi>Publick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility</hi> being the ſcope of the <hi>Law-giver,</hi> or which ought to be in all his Laws) as hath been before ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified and ſettled; And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, whether it <hi>Be,</hi> or <hi>be Not</hi> ſo, (as whether it <hi>Be</hi> (more predominantly) or <hi>Not</hi> agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>God's Word</hi>) is, for the moſt part, therefore, the chief point to be inquired into, as to the <hi>Obligation</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in theſe matters Any Man may be <hi>made</hi> to do the thing for fear of <hi>Wrath,</hi> whether <hi>Juſtice</hi> or <hi>People:</hi> So that, if the Supream Power will have it, they muſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109917:40"/> do it, or Suffer, all Reſiſtance being forbidden; (and as for the <hi>Law,</hi> it is all one whether a Man <hi>act</hi> out of <hi>Conſcience</hi> or <hi>not,</hi> ſo long as it makes him do it): But if a Man, really in his Soul, does judge the thing Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be againſt the <hi>Common Good,</hi> the <hi>Juſtice</hi> that <hi>Executes</hi> not that <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Man</hi> that <hi>Obeys</hi> it not (if they can eſcape with Man) are not obliged for <hi>Conſcience</hi>-ſake (even, as when they think it againſt <hi>God's Will;</hi> for <hi>God's Will,</hi> indeed, is, that Men ſhould Rule only for our Good), ſo as they need think, by that Omiſſion, they <hi>Sin</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>God.</hi> I pray, note all the way, I ſpeak ſtill, not of what
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109917:40"/> is <hi>ſafe</hi> in point of <hi>Law,</hi> but of what is <hi>Innocent</hi> in point of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> And when I allow a <hi>Private</hi> Man to <hi>judge</hi> of a Law, whether it be for the <hi>Publick Good</hi> or <hi>not,</hi> this is not to have a hand in determining the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether I am obliged or not to obey it, under the <hi>Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> but under the <hi>Guilt</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>God's Judgment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither muſt I forget to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh from that well Studied Divine, Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> upon the <hi>Church,</hi> between <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> and conſequently, between the <hi>not Obeying a Law,</hi> and <hi>Reſiſting of Authority;</hi> the latter whereof is made always
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109917:41"/> Damnable by the <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> and the former is <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> or <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> according to the <hi>Matter</hi> required, with conſideration of the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> a Man is in. And, though I am perſwaded (as to the point of <hi>Obedience</hi>), that when a <hi>Law</hi> is unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that is, when a Man does Impartially judge the Matter Commanded, not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to Publick Benefit, (or, at leaſt, if he truly judge the ſame to be againſt it), ſuch a Law <hi>does not,</hi> ſuch a Law <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> oblige the <hi>Inner Man</hi> (which all wholſom Laws, I hold, do) any farther than to avoid <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> and <hi>Scandal:</hi> Yet do I (in the point of <hi>Subjection</hi>)
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:109917:41"/> hold and maintain, and am ready (ſo far as it may concern me) to declare, That I hold it <hi>unlawful</hi> for any Subject, or Subjects, to <hi>take Arms</hi> (that is, Levy War) againſt the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> (that is, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Supream Executive Power, which <hi>God</hi> hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into his hands, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Conſtitution of this Realm), whether as Reſiding in his <hi>Perſon,</hi> or iſſued out from Him to any other Perſon or Perſons, by his <hi>Commiſſions,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any <hi>Pretence whatſoever.</hi> Which I do declare the rather, becauſe I am out of doubt, that thoſe they call <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> as well as the <hi>Conformiſts,</hi> who
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109917:42"/> underſtand themſelves on both ſides, (however it comes to paſs, that One Party of them are ſcrupled for want of but ſo little Explication as this is), are perfectly reconcileable on that Point.</p>
            <p>To conclude, The <hi>Law</hi> in ſuch or ſuch a particular Caſe, requires the <hi>Juſtice</hi> to act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Common Good:</hi> What muſt he do then? I ſpeak not of what he may <hi>chooſe</hi> to do, in point of <hi>Prudence</hi> (which, in caſe a <hi>Law</hi> is directly againſt <hi>God</hi>'s, or ſo extreamly to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick hurt, as quite over-bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances our Sufferings, is not to be conſulted); but of what
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109917:42"/> he is <hi>bound</hi> to, in point of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> And every one, I think, will give this Anſwer, That the <hi>Superiour</hi> Law muſt have ſtill the <hi>Preheminence,</hi> unleſs there be ſomething particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be alledged, in regard to that Matter; which is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionable in the Caſe, if it be againſt <hi>God's Word.</hi> He muſt himſelf judge in referrence to his own <hi>Act,</hi> or he acts as a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and <hi>Puniſhes</hi> as an Horſe <hi>ſtrikes.</hi> And he is alſo the <hi>Miniſter of God,</hi> under the <hi>King,</hi> for the <hi>Peoples Good.</hi> This is the very End Of <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> it ſelf, Of the <hi>Laws,</hi> Of the <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Conſequently, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good, <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> being
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109917:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Supream Law; whoſoever he be that ſincerely ſeeks That, whether he <hi>Executes</hi> or <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears</hi> a Statute, he is, he muſt be, in the Forbearance or Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution thereof, upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, the beſt Miniſter Of the <hi>Laws,</hi> Of <hi>God,</hi> and Of the <hi>King: Princeps eſt Dei imago; Lex Principis opus; Finis Legis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia; Ex Juſtitia Communis Salus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Deo Gloria.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 9. Line 8. for <hi>fieris</hi> read <hi>feceris</hi> p. 20. l. 7. for <hi>prevent</hi> r. <hi>pervert.</hi> p. 45. l. 3. for <hi>are</hi> r. <hi>may be.</hi> p. 57. l. 9. for <hi>forbid</hi> r. <hi>forbad.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
